<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Directions about preparing for death</title>
            <author>Burroughes, Thomas, b. 1611 or 12.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27358</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37044</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16187710</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16187710</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105036</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27358)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105036)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1085:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Directions about preparing for death</title>
                  <author>Burroughes, Thomas, b. 1611 or 12.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Maxwell for John Baker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: T.B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Consolation.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105036:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105036:1"/>
            <p>DIRECTIONS ABOUT PREPARING FOR DEATH</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eccleſ. 11.8.</hi>
               </bibl> If a man live many yeers, and rejoyce in them all; yet let him remember the days of darkneſs, for they ſhall be many: All that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is vanity.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Maxwell,</hi> for <hi>John Baker</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in <hi>Little-Brittain, Anno. Dom.</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:105036:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105036:2"/>
            <head>To the much Honoured, Sir <hi>John Langham,</hi> Knight and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured Sir.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TIS now about ſix yeers ſince, that, at your Deſire, and for your own private uſe, I penned the following ſhort, and plain Directions; your appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of your approching change being the occaſion. For though, God hath been pleaſed to exempt you from very many of the uſual Conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitants of old Age (ſo that you have not known, nor do to this day, what they mean, by your own experience;) yet the very Number of your Years, and the weakneſs you find creeping on you, (though, through Gods mercy, joyned with
<pb facs="tcp:105036:3"/>a good meaſure of Health) cannot but mind you of your long Home, (Ecc. <hi>12.5.</hi>) and give you to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that there is but a little of your Glaſs to run. And as I was, by your deſire, put upon the Writing of the enſuing little piece, ſo am I now, upon the Printing of it. And if it may prove more publickly uſeful, than I firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, I ſhall have cauſe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg the Divine Goodneſs therein, and to bleſs God for it. Now the Lord graciouſly help you in your preparations for your Eternal State; (which you do well to be much thinking of;) grant unto you, <hi>that you may find mercy in that day: (2 Tim. 1.18.)</hi> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply his Favours Spiritual and Temporal upon your poſterity, and make them all great bleſſings, in their ſeveral ſtations: That being happy Inſtruments of Gods Glory
<pb facs="tcp:105036:3"/>in this World, they may be Veſſels of Glory in that which is to come. This is the unfained and daily Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
               <signed>your very much obliged Servant in the Lord. T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105036:4"/>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:105036:4"/>
            <head>Directions about Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for Death.</head>
            <p>THERE is but one, and the ſame Direction for living Well, and dying Comfortably. And therefore the Holy Scripture, which was given to inſtruct us, How <hi>to order our converſations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.23.) hath in teaching us that Leſſon, ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently withal taught us the other too. A good Life cannot but have a bleſſed Concluſion. <hi>The end of the upright man</hi> (ſure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) <hi>ſhall be peace</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.37.) And doubtleſs, that man's
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105036:5"/>
               <hi>Hope</hi> is likely to prove no better than a <hi>Spider's web,</hi> (<hi>Job.</hi> 18.14.) who expects <hi>to reap mercy from God</hi> at his latter end, and yet, in the days of his health, makes no proviſion, <hi>by ſowing in right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eouſneſs</hi> for ſuch an Harveſt. (<hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 32.17.) Our Souls are not to be Bequeathed to God as a Legacy, at Death, but Soul and Body, and all we have, ought to be devoted to him, and his ſervice, in our Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and throughout the whole courſe of our lives from firſt to laſt, (<hi>Ecc.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 2.10.) Yet, I dare not abſolutely affirm, that a Death-bed Repentance is invalid: but this is ſure; He that deferrs his Repentance till then, will be hard put to it, even to ſatisfie himſelf, about his own ſincerity, if his Conſcience be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake. That which a man gives
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105036:5"/>not till he be neceſſitated, is no proof of his Liberality. And, if to put off our turning to God, and reſignation of our ſelves to him, till we be arreſted by Death, be a ſign of our Love, 'tis hard to tell, what Argument there can be of a mind Alienated from Him. Yet I ſhould be far from diſcouraging any man (as I ſaid) from entertaining thoughts <hi>of turning from his evil ways,</hi> as if there were no hope for him; for who <hi>can tell but God may ſhew mercy? (Jonah</hi> 3.8, 9.) How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever this is certain: <hi>To get our Hearts mortified to the World, to ſue out our pardon through the Blood of Chriſt, to Believe and Repent, to Reform our ways, to be Holy, Righteous and Sober, to work out our Salvation with fear and trembling, to make our Calling and Election ſure,</hi> are not only
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105036:6"/>works for Dying men, but they are every mans Duty, even <hi>to day</hi> while it is called to day <hi>(Heb.</hi> 3.13, 15.) The Living, the Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, the Strong, the Young, as well as the Aged are to learn theſe Leſſons, while their parts are vigorous, while their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, memory, ſenſes, are beſt able to perform their ſeveral Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; Functions. Theſe are things concern all, (ſo, as nothing more) as well, when they are apt fondly to imagine that Enemie Death a great way off, as when they have cauſe to think, they hear the ſound of his Feet at the Door.</p>
            <p>How ſadly then do thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons delude and abuſe themſelves (and God knows there be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of ſuch) who have a ſtrong fancy, that they may, all the while they live, balk the way of Gods precepts (thoſe <hi>paths of pleaſantneſs</hi> to the <hi>ſpiritually-minded,</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105036:6"/>but rugged and tedious to ſuch <hi>as are carnal, (Pro.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.) and yet find <hi>a ſhort cut</hi> to Heaven when they dye? And in the ſtrength of this Fancy do adventure to run perfectly counter to the direction of our Bleſſed Saviour <hi>(Mat.</hi> 6.33) ſeeking to make ſure of other things firſt, and moſt preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly promiſing themſelves, that the Kingdom of Heaven ſhall be added to them at laſt? This, I know, they do in love to their fleſh, and that they may <hi>make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions for it,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks <hi>(Rom.</hi> 13.14.) but it is a moſt dreadful thing, that a man, in favour to his fleſh, ſhould be thus cruel to his own Soul, <hi>hardning himſelf againſt it as if it were none of his</hi> (as we read <hi>Job.</hi> 39.14-18. the Oſtrich ſerves her young ones) being ſo, wholly uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105036:7"/>about his own Eternal Welfare and Woe.</p>
            <p>But to let theſe men paſs: As for ſuch as are ſpiritually-wiſe, they will not be tempted to run ſuch hazzards; They will be careful, with all ſpeed, to do thoſe things, which others when they come to dye, ſhall wiſh they had done. Not but that the Beſt of men have their failings, which they are ſenſible of, and ſee cauſe to be deeply humbled for <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 19.12.) notwithſtanding their greateſt care to work out their Salvation, that they may have nothing to do, when Death comes, but to Dye. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though, when their laſt hour is at hand, they have no new work (for the main) to go about, but only that to go over again, which every Chriſtian is, or ſhould have been, accuſtomed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105036:7"/>to, long before; yet they know it concerns them to beſtir them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (with the wiſe Virgins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.7.) <hi>In trimming their Lamps,</hi> and that ſo much the more, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Night is approaching (Joh.</hi> 9.4.) Though therefore they have oft ſearched their Hearts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into their ſpiritual eſtate, they now do it again, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view their lives, they examine how matters ſtand between God, and their ſouls; they conſid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er what account they ſhall give of their Stewardſhip, they look over their Evidences for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and ſtir up themſelvs to exerciſe their Faith, and renew their Repentance; they labour, by Meditation, to get a proſpect of the promiſed Land, that hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Hearts diſ-intangled from the Creature, they may bid adieu to this vain World, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105036:8"/>their ſouls may, chearfully and with comfort, take their flight to thoſe <hi>Bleſſed Manſions above.</hi> That this is the right way of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for death, I am now to ſhew ſomewhat more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But firſt, it will be needful, for me, to ſpeak of the cauſes of that (I ſhould call it ſtupendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, if it were not common) unpreparedneſs, and unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that is in the moſt, as to their death and departure hence, when as yet they know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, it is unavoidable. Now the cauſes here of are principally, and chiefly three, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Their inordinate and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Love of this preſent World, and the enjoyments of it, from which they are loth to let go their Hold.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſcience of ſin, and the ſad Apprehenſions they have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105036:8"/>of the Guilt, under which they lye.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And Conſequently, the great uncertainty they are in, of what will become of them in the next World. For if our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were weaned (as they ſhould be) from things below; had we ſome good aſſurance, our ſins were pardoned, and that we ſhould be happy in the world to come; there would be ſo little of terrour in death, that we ſhould be willing and ready, at a days, at an hours-warning, to lay down our <hi>earthly Houſe of this Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, in hope of an houſe made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands, eternal in the Heavens,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, 2.) and hardly any more afraid to dye, than we uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally are to compoſe our ſelves to ſleep, when night is come.</p>
            <p>That we may therefore be in a continual preparedneſs for our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105036:9"/>laſt hour, and able to welcome Death cheerfully, when ever it ſhall ſummon us to be gone hence; Three things are to be done.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt, out of hand, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with our hearts to make them dead to all things ſubluna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; our profits, honours, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, even all our earthly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We muſt, with all ſpeed, and importunity, ſue out our pardon, at the Throne of Grace, through the Blood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt daily be giving all diligence to make our Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on more and more ſure, and to work out our Salvation. And thus doing, whether the <hi>Master of the Houſe come at even, or at Midnight, or at Cock-crowing, or in the Morning,</hi> (as 'tis <hi>Mark</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.35.) we ſhall be in a readineſs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105036:9"/>for him, and received by him <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his joy, (Mat.</hi> 25.21.)</p>
            <p n="1">1. To begin with the firſt: It is not poſſible, we ſhould ever be ready, and willing, when God calls us hence, to leave the world, if we have not firſt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>to uſe it, as if we uſed it not</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31.) For if our hearts be ſet upon theſe preſent things, and we engaged in an over-eager purſuit, and proſecution of them, it will be as death to us, before we dye, to think of parting with them, and bidding them an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Adieu. And yet alas, this is the Temper of all the Sons of <hi>Adam;</hi> the profits and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and accommodations of this Life, whether they enjoy (in hopes, or poſſeſſion) little or much of them, ſeem very great things in their eyes and eſteem: And 'tis natural to them
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105036:10"/>to prize and value them above meaſure. <hi>The Love of the World, and of the things in the World,</hi> is ſo prevalent with the moſt, that, if it were put to their choyce, they would be for liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here, always, and not care for any better, or any other Heaven. To have their Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, on this ſide of <hi>Jordan,</hi> would pleaſe them beſt, if it might be granted to them, <hi>here to abide, and here to have a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing City. (Heb.</hi> 13.14.) Till a mans heart therefore be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe affected, the thoughts of removing hence muſt needs be bitter, and unpleaſing, and let any one judg, how ſuch a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is likely to be prepared for his <hi>Great change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to looſen our affections from the Creature, two things are requiſite:</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105036:10"/>1. Serious and Deep Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Fervent and Frequent Prayer.</p>
            <p>Two things are to be chafed into our hearts, by often Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating on them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How <hi>empty and vain,</hi> all theſe inferiour things are.</p>
            <p n="2">2. How much <hi>better things</hi> by far, and more worthy our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, there are to be enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the <hi>Vanity</hi> of all things under the Sun, it cannot be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſet forth, than by thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, which <hi>Solomon</hi> (who was inſpired by the Holy-Ghoſt to write on this Subject) uſeth in the firſt Chap. of <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> I ſhall mention only four of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>What profit</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.3.) <hi>hath a man of all his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105036:11"/>which he taketh under the Sun?</hi> Which is as if he had ſaid, He hath none at all, or that which next to none. When a man with his buſtling and taking pains, and diſtracting cares, by day and by night, hath run out his preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous time, waſted his ſtrength, worn out his body, and tired himſelf; Let him but ſit down (a while) and caſt up his accounts, (to ſee what he hath purchaſed) and he will find, that <hi>Solomon</hi> hath adjuſted them right to his hand, in the Text laſt cited, and that (upon the whole) <hi>He hath no profit,</hi> that is, none compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, none worth ſpeaking of. For,</p>
            <p>Suppoſe a man hath gotten, <hi>by his labour under the Sun,</hi> as much as any ever did: Yet,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, When all's done, In many reſpects, he is ſtill but upon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105036:11"/>the <hi>ſame terms</hi> with thoſe of his Neighbours, that have not (hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) the Hundredth or the Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſandth part of what he enjoys. He is ſtill as ſubject to diſeaſes, weakneſſes, and pains; he lyes as open (for all his Honour or Eſtate) to the Calamities of Mankind, to the loſs of his moſt intimate Friends, of his deareſt Children, and moſt belov'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and may, every whit aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoon, be croſſed and afflicted in them, as the meaneſt perſon. He can no more <hi>ranſom from going to the Grave, (Pſal.</hi> 49.7.) yea or procure a reprieve, for any he moſt tenderly loves, than the pooreſt Man. Honour, and Riches, are no fence at all to the Owners of them, or to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies from the Feaver, the ſmall Pox, the G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut, the Stone, or from the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>ence it ſelf, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105036:12"/>innumerable Evils more. A man, by all <hi>the Labour he takes under the Sun,</hi> hath in ſuch caſes as theſe, (and many beſide, that might be nam'd) no priviledg, more than thoſe of a lower con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; nor is he raiſed, one jot, above the Level of them, whom he uſeth to look upon as his Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlings, Thus far, therefore, <hi>A man hath no profit of all the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour he takes under the Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But then again further: He that hath the greateſt ſhare of theſe earthly things, doth, in many regards, ſtand, upon <hi>worſe terms</hi> than thoſe do, who enjoy much leſs of them. He is oft perplexed with thoſe <hi>Cares, Anxieties, Vexations, Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments, and Fears,</hi> that others, in a lower ſtation, are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with; And is expoſed to thoſe <hi>Inconveniences and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:105036:12"/>(who can number them all?) from which his inferiors are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd. <hi>The ſleep of the labouring man is ſweet, but the abundance of the rich will not ſuffer him to ſleep in quiet. (Eccl.</hi> 5.12.) Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, the larger portion of theſe outward things any one enjoys, the more ſtill he is envy'd. And who, that obſervs any thing of the affairs of the World, is not able from his own experience, to produce inſtances good ſtore, of the trueth of that which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith <hi>(Pro.</hi> 27.4.) that <hi>None can ſtand before envy.</hi> The high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Cedars (as 'tis well known) are moſt ſubject to be ſtricken with Thunder, and moſt expos'd to winds and tempeſts, which the lower ſhrubs are not ſo moleſted with; And yet, all this while, I have not mention'd (that which is worſe) <hi>thoſe many ſorrows,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:105036:13"/>that ſuch perſons (as I now ſpeak of) are wont <hi>to pierce themſelvs through with,</hi> and <hi>thoſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſnares, and many fooliſh and hurtful luſts</hi> (which they are more liable <hi>to fall into)</hi> and <hi>which drown men in deſtruction, and perdition,</hi> (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9, 10.) if the infinite mercy of God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent them not. So true an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation is that of the wiſe man <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.13.) that <hi>riches are</hi> oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en <hi>kept for the owners of them to their hurt.</hi> And in this reſpect alſo, we may well repeat the former queſtion, <hi>What profit hath a Man of all his Labour which he taketh under the Sun?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And yet Thirdly, Thoſe things wherein ſuch (as have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the moſt of what this World affords) are priviledg'd above other, are but few. <hi>(A Child may count them, Eſa.</hi> 10.19.)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105036:13"/>and ſo ſmall, if duely conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they conſiſt more in Fancy than Reality. <hi>The Rich mans wealth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon Pro.</hi> 18.11.) <hi>is a strong City, and an high Wall</hi> (but withal he adds that 'tis ſo) <hi>in his own Conceit.</hi> And this appears, by what he tells us <hi>(Ecc.</hi> 5.11.) <hi>When goods are increaſed, they are increaſed that eat them; and what good is there to the owners thereof, ſaving the beholding of them with their eyes?</hi> This is (it ſeems) one chief advantage of a man, in the midſt of his Abundance: And how much is there in it, more than Fancy? Beſide, <hi>The rich</hi> (as we are told, <hi>Pro.</hi> 4.20.) <hi>have many friends;</hi> and that's another of their priviledges. But it is to be underſtood, of ſuch as pretend and make a ſhew to be ſo. For <hi>a friend</hi> (indeed) <hi>loveth at all
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105036:14"/>times (Pro.</hi> 17.17.) And how few there be, that uſe to ſtick to ſuch perſons, when they are no longer, in a capacity <hi>to give gifts, (Pro.</hi> 19.6.) daily experience makes ſo evident, that it needs no further proof. Their <hi>Honour and Reſpect</hi> is another thing, wherein they have the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence above their Neighbours; but who knows not that to be a thing, rather in the <hi>perſon ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring, than the perſon honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> And if there be not ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward real worth, that is the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of it, who but a fool can be pleas'd and taken with it? 'Tis true, if a man improve his Wealth and Reſpect, and Accomodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to make him ſo much the more ſerviceable to God (as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are not otherwiſe of any value) he may by his well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing of theſe things, <hi>lay up a good
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105036:14"/>foundation of comfort</hi> to his ſoul (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.19.) againſt the time to come, and provide for his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in another World. But that muſt be (as 'tis in the Text laſt cited) by his being <hi>rich in good works, ready to diſtribute, willing to communicate,</hi> and that from a principle of Faith, and Love, and with ſincere reſpect to Gods Glory. It muſt be, by outſtripping others, as much in doing good, as he goes beyond them in Eſtate and Authority, by doing as much ſervice to God, as an hundred others, when he hath an hundred times as much as they; otherwiſe his Reckonings will be but the more heavy, when he ſhall be required to give <hi>an Account of his Stewardſhip. (Luk.</hi> 16.2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.19-23.) So far ſhall he be from being, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a whit, in the better caſe for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105036:15"/>all his enjoyments! ſo that, let a man have never <hi>ſo great an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance,</hi> unleſs God give him <hi>wiſdom</hi> alſo <hi>(Ecc.</hi> 7.11.) to trade for things <hi>Eternal,</hi> with <hi>Temporal,</hi> we may ſtill ask as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> doth <hi>What profit hath he?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Another Argument, the wiſeman makes uſe of, to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate <hi>the Emptineſs</hi> of the things under the Sun (the point in hand) is taken from <hi>Mans Mortality. (Ecc.</hi> 1.4.) <hi>One Generation goes, and another comes, but the Earth endures.</hi> Suppoſe a man, by his Labour, had got any Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations, which could, more or leſs, contribute to his profit; yet this is the miſery, he cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy them long. If they <hi>make not themſelves wings, and flee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> as very often they do <hi>(Pro.</hi> 23.5.) before their owners be aware; 'tis certain, he muſt <hi>ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105036:15"/>flee away, from</hi> them, <hi>as a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,</hi> (ſo we read <hi>Job.</hi> 14.2.) <hi>here he muſt not continue.</hi> The Earth, indeed, abides and hath done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt theſe 6000. years; but one Generation treads upon the heels of another; and we ſee by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of all times, one thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth another off the Stage. Once within an hundred years, there's a perfect riddance made of all the Inhabitants of the Earth, and others come in their room: God dealing with the Earth, as one doth with <hi>a diſh, that he wipeth and turneth upſide down,</hi> empty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it of what was in it before, (according to that expreſſion 2 <hi>King.</hi> 21.13.) The whole World is but a great, and common Inn, where every hour ſome are new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entring, and others are going out, and no body ſtays very long. Every day, thouſands are crowd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105036:16"/>into the World, and thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of paſſing Bells are daily tolling, to give notice that others are haſting out as faſt. How fain would a man live to ſee this Child, and that Child, diſpoſed of, and ſetled, and then would fain ſtay a little longer to ſee his Childrens Children, and yet a little longer to ſee his Poſterity planted, and taking root and ſpreading abroad: And how apt is he to pleaſe himſelf with ſuch thoughts as theſe, till Death come upon him like an armed man, as poverty and want ſeize upon the ſluggard while he is yawning out, <hi>Yet a little ſleep, a little ſlumber?</hi> (<hi>Pro.</hi> 6.10.) For here no man muſt be permitted to linger long, or take up his Reſt; we muſt all pack up, and be gone. <hi>Who is he that liveth, and ſhall not ſee Death? Who can deliver his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:105036:16"/>ſoul from the hand of the Grave?</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 89 48.) No perſon, of what Quality or Condition ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, hath in this particular any prerogative more than the poor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Beggar. Thoſe who, for their eminency above others, are ſometimes, in Scripture, <hi>called gods,</hi> (even the higheſt of them) muſt for all that, <hi>dye like other men,</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.6.7.) The Clay-Cottages of ſome few, indeed, may be a little more tight, and ſo laſt a little longer than other mens do: but there is a period fixt for all (known only to God) beyond which they cannot paſs; and when that hour is come, God ſaith but the word and it is done, <hi>Return to your dust ye Children of men,</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.3.) To ſtruggle, or hang back is to no purpoſe. Now what an exceeding great Vanity is this! For,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:105036:17"/>1. Ere a man can come to reap the fruit (he deſires) of what he hath ſowed and ſpent his ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and labour about, Death is upon him, and he muſt be gone. And though he would give all his Eſtate for a few yeers reprieve, though he would never ſo fain be reſpited, for a little while longer, till he might ſee ſuch or ſuch a buſineſs diſpatcht, it will not be granted. How often falls it out, that a man brings ſome Project (which he was long in travel with) to that forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that there wants but little more than the laying of the Top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and yet Death forceth him to leave his work imperfect? How frequently is it ſeen that, when a man is now going to taſt the ſweet of ſome Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (that he hath been ſome yeers labouring for, and hath
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:105036:17"/>gotten at length) Death comes on a ſudden, and daſheth the cup out of his hand, before it touches his lips? How uſually doth it happen, that when a man begins to ſing, <hi>Soul, take thine eaſe, thou haſt much goods laid up,</hi> he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently diſturbed by hearing a voice ſaying, <hi>Thou fool this night ſhall thy ſoul be required of thee?</hi> (Luk. 12.19, 20.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> All theſe things which he hath toiled and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for, he muſt leave behind him; and the word of God tells him <hi>He knows not for whom,</hi> Pſal. 39.6. He hopes indeed they ſhall be for ſuch as he himſelf hath deſign'd, but daily <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> as well as the <hi>Scripture,</hi> ſhews that's a thing no man hath any certainty of. To be ſure, <hi>As he came naked into the world, ſo again naked he must return,</hi> Job.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:105036:18"/>1.21. <hi>And when he dieth he ſhall carry nothing away, his glory and his riches ſhall not deſcend af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him,</hi> Pſal. 49.17. All things in the world being in this reſpect like thoſe ſtanders, that a man muſt leave behind him, when he removes from one houſe to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And this the wiſe man takes notice of <hi>as a ſore evil, that a man ſhall take nothing of his labour, which he may carry away in his hand; but in all points, as he came, ſo ſhall he go;</hi> and from hence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrs, <hi>What profit hath he that thus laboured for the wind?</hi> Eccleſ. 5.15, 16. Now if the caſe be thus, can the things of this world be fit Objects for an Immortal Soul to doat upon? Or, is there any likelihood they ſhould contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Satisfaction of ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Being, any more than Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelf, would be able to do?</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:105036:18"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly. Solomon</hi>'s next Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove the point we are ſpeaking of, ſeems to be taken from the very <hi>Constitution</hi> and <hi>frame</hi> of this world, and its ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts: <hi>The Sun riſeth and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth down, and hasteth to the place where he aroſe. The Wind go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the South, and turneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to the North; it whirleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout continually. All Rivers run into the Sea; unto the place, whence the Rivers come, thither do they return again. All things are full of labour,</hi> (<hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.5, 6, 7, 8.) that is; The World and all the parts of it are ſo conſtituted and framed, that they do proclaim to <hi>every one that hath ears to hear, Ariſe, begone, this is not your reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place,</hi> (Mic. 2.10.) Let any man that <hi>hath eyes to ſee,</hi> but look about him, and ſuppoſe he were askt the queſtion, that was put to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:105036:19"/>
               <hi>Jeremy,</hi> (chap. 1.11, 13.) <hi>What ſeest thou?</hi> What could he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, but I ſee the Sun, the Wind, the Sea, and all Creatures in a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual hurry &amp; agitation; nothing keeps the ſame face for a day together, without ſome alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And what of this? Why, doth this look like the place, where Happineſs is to be found? Do not all Creatures, with one voice, proclaim aloud, that <hi>All is vanity?</hi> and that we muſt ſeek ſomewhere elſe, for that felicity we pant and gaſp after? Certainly there are no ſuch Viciſſitudes and Changes, there is no ſuch unqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs in the place appointed for Man's eternal Reſt. If we were but <hi>conſiderative,</hi> and would but <hi>ſhow our ſelves men</hi> (as the Holy Ghoſt ſpeaks, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 46.8.) we might eaſily gather and collect from hence, that here below is
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:105036:19"/>nothing but Vanity, and that Creatures and Creature-comforts were never ordained by God, for thoſe ends, that men in their folly think to make them ſerve for. Give but a ſuit of Apparel to an <hi>Indian</hi> that goes naked, and is not acquainted with ſuch clothes as we wear, and let him but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the frame and make of them, and he will eaſily gueſs by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the ſeveral parts of it, with the parts of his body, which was, and which was not, made for each. And if we did but ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly compare what's to be had in this World and our Souls to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, might we not as eaſily find it out, that things here below were never made for them; and that their only uſe is, to give us a little Accommodations for our Bodies, and that but for a while? Might we not ſoon diſcern, that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:105036:20"/>here is not any thing to be had, which will do the ſoul good, or conduce to its welfare? and therefore that, as to ſuch a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>All things are Vanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A fourth Argument, by which the Preacher demonſtrates how empty all things under the Sun are, is the little, or rather the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfaction that they do All af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford. <hi>The eye</hi> (ſaith he, <hi>chap.</hi> 1 8.) <hi>is not ſatisfied with ſeeing, nor the ear with hearing.</hi> And he argues thus from the leſs, If <hi>the eye and the ear</hi> cannot be ſatisfied with things ſeen and heard, betwixt which yet there is ſome proportion; much leſs can the Mind and Soul of Man be filled with any thing ſublunary, betwixt which there is no proportion at all. Now the Eye though it have ſeen never ſo much, would fain ſee more, &amp; the ear would learn and diſcover
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:105036:20"/>ſomething further, and is ſtill liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning after ſome new thing. The moſt pleaſing Objects (in a little while) grow ſtale, and we are weary of them. A man may look upon that he delights in till his eye-ſtrings crack, e're he have his fill, break his neck (as one ſaith) ſooner than his faſt on earthly contentments. Men quickly grow to a loathing of what they have moſt importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately longed for, and have no ſooner got what they did eagerly deſire, but would preſently fain have ſomething elſe. We pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe our ſelves great matters while we are in expectation of ſuch and ſuch things; but we find not that in the fruition which we looked for. The contentment we have in the things of this World is from the Fancy we have of what is in them, while we
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:105036:21"/>behold them at a diſtance, but the nearer we come to them the leſs we ſee in them to be taken with. <hi>He that feedeth on them feedeth on aſhes, and he hath no better than a lie in his right hand, (Eſa.</hi> 44.20.) Now thus it would not be, if they were not meer emptineſs and vanity. Where happineſs is, there is full and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat ſatisfaction without any nauſeating. There the deſires of the ſoul are all rectifi'd, and no one of them meets with diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment. But this World is not the place where, nor the Accomdations of this World, the things wherein felicity is to be found. As to that purpoſe, <hi>All's but Vanity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe things, and ſuch as theſe we muſt often and ſeriouſly me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate on, that we may learn (to uſe the Apoſtles expreſſion, <hi>Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:105036:21"/>12.3.) <hi>not to think</hi> of the Profits and Honour, and Pleaſures of this life, <hi>more highly than we ought to think,</hi> and then they will be no hindrance to us in our Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for death.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But ſecondly we muſt alſo (as I ſaid) by Meditation labour to get our hearts affected with thoſe Things within the Vail. Thoſe infinitely better things that are to be enjoyed in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World; yea, and in this life too, as to the firſt-fruits, and Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſts of them. Such are thoſe Graces that <hi>make us rich towards God,</hi> (Luk. 12.21.) thoſe Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours that are confer'd by Him, in <hi>making us his friends, &amp; adopting us for his Sons, and co-heirs with Chriſt,</hi> (Joh. 15.14. Jam. 2.23. Rom. 8.17.) Thoſe pleaſures which conſiſt in <hi>Communion and Fellowſhip with Him, and with his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:105036:22"/>Son the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.3.) Of ſuch things as thoſe, the ſoul is capable; &amp; in them conſiſts its Life and Peace, and Comfort here, and Happineſs hereafter. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of Meats, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.13.) ſaith, <hi>The belly is for them, and they for the belly &amp; both muſt periſh.</hi> But theſe are things fitted for the Immortal Soul of Man, and for which the Soul was made, and both endure unto E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity. They fill the heart with <hi>joy unſpeakable and glorious,</hi> (1 Pet. 1.18.) a joy that's laſting and will hold; whereas that which ariſeth from worldly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments, is but like the blaze of a little bruſh-wood, that is ſoon extinguiſhed, <hi>(Eccleſ.</hi> 7.6.) The ſerious apprehenſions of theſe things will make us <hi>as weaned</hi> children, <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 131.2.) toward things below, and work in us a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:105036:22"/>longing <hi>deſire to be diſſolved and to be with Christ,</hi> (Phil. 1.23.) that we may have the full enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what we now hope for. So as we ſhall be ready to ſay with <hi>Austin</hi>'s Mother, when ſhe had heard a diſcourſe of the Glory above, <hi>What do I here then?</hi> and with <hi>Simeon,</hi> to welcome death and ſay, <hi>Lord, now letteſt thou thy ſervant depart in peace.</hi> The ſtrong and reſtleſs inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Souls in ſeeking hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, do certainly ſhew that there is to be found, ſome where that which will ſatisfie it; if this world yield it not, ſure enough the other doth. The Childs eyes and ears, and the other Organs of his Sences are framed we know) even when it is in the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers womb; and yet, while it is there, it finds not Objects for them. But yet this very thing,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:105036:23"/>that God hath given it thoſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, is proof ſufficient that he hath prepared Objects ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where elſe. And when the Child comes into the world he meets with them.</p>
            <p>Thus it is in the preſent caſe: we may be ſure God would not have put that unceſſant, earneſt, and unwearied longing after Happineſs, into our Souls, if he had not alſo provided that which might fully ſatisfie us; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may be certain, though in this life we find it not, (Riches and Honours, and Pleaſures, have it not in them) yet in another world there is that to be had, which here we do ſo reſtleſlypant and gaſp after. If our affections were taken with theſe things, Death (which is but the Saints paſſage to the fulneſs of theſe joys) would not be dreadful to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:105036:23"/>us, nor ſhould we be unprepar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As we muſt Meditate much and often upon theſe eternal things; ſo we muſt be earneſt, and importunate in <hi>Prayer,</hi> with God, to take off our Hearts, from the creature, and to draw them forth to Himſelf. <q>Lord, thou haſt made the creatures for me, and my uſe, but haſt not made me for them. Thou haſt given me a noble and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Soul, that is capable of communion with thine own Majeſty. Thou haſt made my Heart for thy Bleſſed Self, and I find it is reſtleſs, and for ever will be ſo, till I come <hi>to enjoy Thes, (Pſal.</hi> 73.22.) Ah! how <hi>fooliſhly</hi> have I miſpent the greateſt part of my days, in <hi>digging broken Ciſterns, that can hold no water, (Jer.</hi> 2.13.)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:105036:24"/>while, in the <hi>mean ſeaſon, I have forſaken thee who art the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of living water!</hi> How have I <hi>wearyed</hi> my ſelf <hi>in following after the Wind! (Hoſ.</hi> 12.1.) How hath my head and heart been filled and perplexed with cares, and thoughts, about e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing almoſt, ſave that <hi>one thing neceſſary! (Luk.</hi> 10.42.) I have been ſolicitous about my eſtate, about my honour, about my Accommodations here, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout providing, that I and mine, might live in <hi>repute and eaſe;</hi> but Ah! How hath my <hi>Soul</hi> and the concernments of it (mean while) been neglected by me! And now, Lord, what doth all this advantage me! How true is that which thou haſt told me in thy word, <hi>that a man hath no profit of all that wherein he hath laboured under
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:105036:24"/>the Sun? (Ecc.</hi> 1.3.) Death is at hand, the <hi>Judgſtands</hi> before the door, I ſhall be called, I know not how ſoon to give an <hi>Account</hi> of my ſtewardſhip; <hi>I muſt ſhortly go hence and return to my houſe no more, nor ſhall my place know me any more (Job.</hi> 7.10.) <hi>And as I brought nothing into the world with me, ſo must I carry nothing away of all I have</hi> (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.7.) and if I could, what would it avail me, or do me good? Lord, I ſee my errors, and my folly, though it be late; and I humbly bleſs thee, that I do ſo, and hope it is not yet too late. Through thy favour, I have enjoyed abundance of thoſe outward mercies, others have wanted; and while thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands have been put to great exigencies and ſtraits, (that have deſerved as well) <hi>My cup
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:105036:25"/>hath overflowed, thou haſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted my head with oyle, and ſpread my Table in the preſence of mine enimies. (Pſal.</hi> 23.5.) But heavenly Father, I truſt thou haſt other and better bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings in ſtore for me, than theſe, and that thou wilt not put me off with <hi>theſe for my portion. (Pſal.</hi> 17.14.) It is thy favour and love, <hi>(Pſal.</hi> 106.4.) <hi>that favour thou bearest to thy choſen</hi> ones, that muſt make me <hi>happy.</hi> I am not, I cannot be ſatisfied with any thing elſe. Oh! be pleaſed to beſtow thy Self upon me. Give me, more and more to ſee, and to be convinced, that the riches, and honours, and accommodations of this preſent life, are no further at all valuable than as opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of doing thee more ſervice than others can do who want
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:105036:25"/>them; and that otherwiſe they are meer vanities, and worſe, and will prove to be ſo at laſt. Give me, to remember they are <hi>but Talents, (Mat.</hi> 25.27.) which thou haſt intruſted me with, not for my own uſe only, but to trade with, for thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and honour, who art my Lord and Maſter, and wilt call for (<hi>v.</hi> 19.) <hi>an account of</hi> them, <hi>as certainly, and more ſtrictly</hi> than ever I called my ſervants to account for any moneys of mine, that I committed into their hands. Lord, give me that wiſdom and faithfulneſs, that I may not be found wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and wittingly failing in my truſt. So convince me of the reality and truth of thoſe things <hi>within the vail,</hi> and ſo poſſeſs my heart with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of the <hi>glory, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:105036:26"/>pleaſures, and full ſatisfaction (Pſal.</hi> 16.11.) <hi>that is to be had in thy preſence, and at thy right hand,</hi> that it may not be at all grievous to me, to part with theſe things below, which are tranſitory; and give me that evidence of my intereſt and part in <hi>theſe Eternal things,</hi> that I may willingly and cheerfully let go my hold of <hi>things Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral,</hi> when thou ſhalt call me hence.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing that is to be done in order to our prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for death, is, with all ſpeed and importunity to ſue out our Pardon at the <hi>throne of Grace.</hi> That which is (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.56.) the <hi>ſting of Death</hi> indeed, and makes it to be ſo terrible, <hi>is ſin.</hi> If ſin be pardoned, death is diſarmed, and cannot hurt us. But, where the Conſcience is loaded with
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:105036:26"/>guilt, and the poor ſinner knows not but that all his Tranſgreſſions will be charged upon him, that all thoſe (<hi>Mat.</hi> 18.24.) <hi>many thouſand talents,</hi> wherein he ſtands indebted to <hi>Gods juſtice,</hi> will be exacted (<hi>Mat.</hi> 5.26.) <hi>to the utmoſt farthing;</hi> He can look upon Death, as no other than a <hi>Serjeant</hi> ſent to <hi>arreſt</hi> him, body and ſoul, and to hale him to that priſon, from whence he muſt never be releaſed, till he hath payd all that he owes; and that will not be, unto <hi>eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what is to be done in this caſe?</p>
            <p>This is firſt to be premiſed; that we have no way left us (by any thing we can give to God, any thing that we can do or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer) to make ſatisfaction, in the leaſt, to Divine juſtice. If a man ſhould, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.3.) <hi>give
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:105036:27"/>all his goods to the poor; if he ſhould give a thouſand Rams, or ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand rivers of Oyl; if he ſhould give the firſt-born of his Body,</hi> (<hi>Mic.</hi> 6.6, 7.) or his own <hi>body to be burnt</hi> for the expiation of the <hi>ſin of his</hi> ſoul, it would not be accepted. There is no way to be freed from the guilt of ſin, but by Gods pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and forgiving it; and that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don is not (as <hi>Job</hi> ſaith of wiſdom, <hi>Job</hi> 28.16, 17, 18, 19.) <hi>to be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for Gold, neither ſhall Silver be weighed for the price of it: it cannot be valued with the Gold of Ophir, with the precious Onyx, or the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phire; the Gold, and the Cryſtal can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not equal it, and the exchange of it ſhall not be for jewels of Gold,</hi> &amp;c. The Blood of the Lord Jeſus <hi>Chriſt, the Lamb of God (Joh.</hi> 1.29.36. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19.) far more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious than Silver and Gold is the only price of it; by that it was procured, by the ſhedding of that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:105036:27"/>blood full <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> hath been made to the juſtice of God; And therefore pardon of ſin, if we would obtain it, is to be ſued out at the Throne of Grace through the blood of that bleſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer of ours.</p>
            <p>The Scripture teacheth us how that is to be done. And the way, which we are there directed to take, is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. With ſorrow and ſhame humbly to confeſs wherein we have done amiſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Earneſtly, and, as for life, to plead Chriſts ſatisfaction, and to beg pardon for his ſake and upon his account.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Confeſſion is to be made to God and that fully, without hiding any of our ſins, chiefly bewailing thoſe whereby we have moſt offended, and which lye heavieſt upon the conſcience,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:105036:28"/>with all the Aggravations of them. <q>Ah Lord! what a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſinner have I been, and how wofully have I gone aſtray from thee! what command of thine is it which I have not bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken! How innumerable are my Omiſſions, my Commiſſions! <hi>Mine iniquities are gone over my head, and as an heavy burden they are too heavy for me to bear,</hi> (Pſ. 38.4.) Whether I look upon my nature, or my life, I have cauſe exceedingly to be confounded. What ſin or wickedneſs is there which I have not the ſeeds of in me, and brought with me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world; I was hewed out of the ſame rock, and digged out of the ſame pit, that <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> and all the reſt of the damned (even the worſt of them) were. That brutiſhneſs, and pride, and ſenſuality, that
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:105036:28"/>prophaneſs and atheiſm, that contempt of thy Majeſty, and thine Ordinances, which do break forth and appear in the lives and ways of ſo many wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches every where; all thoſe wickedneſſes which I have known, or heard committed by any of the Children of <hi>Belial:</hi> Of all theſe evils and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I have the Principles in my curſed nature. Lord! Whoſe underſtanding is more blind, and vain and fooliſh than mine! whoſe Memory is more weak and feeble, more apt to forget Thee, my duty to Thee, my Lord and Saviour, the Things of my Peace; more apt to remember what I ſhould forget, injuries received, things evil or elſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent! How benummed is my Conſcience! How unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably perverſe and rebellious is
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:105036:29"/>my Will? and for my Affections, how unruly and diſordered are they! continually either ſet upon things ſinful, or ſinning when they are carryed out after law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Objects! From this Original Corruption (which hath poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned my whole nature) thou Lord only, knoweſt how many millions of vain, fooliſh, carnal, unclean, uncharitable, impious, prophane, atheiſtical thoughts and imaginations, have daily and hourly iſſued, as ſparks from a burning furnace; <hi>So that every imagination of the thoughts of my heart hath been evil continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> (Gen. 6.5.) <hi>and that from my youth hitherto.</hi> And, bleſſed Lord! I know not (but thou haſt kept an account) how many idle, unſavoury, raſh, beſides wicked and ungodly words, have, upon any occaſions, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:105036:29"/>out of my mouth, from that evil treaſure of my heart within me. Thoſe words are not wind (as many vainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelves) but ſuch, as our bleſſed Saviour tells us <hi>must be reckoned for at the day of judgment,</hi> (Matth. 12.36.) if they be not in earneſt repented of. And, Lord, though here be more than enough and enough again to condemn me everlaſtingly; yet, bleſſed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther! I have not only thought and ſpoken ſo much amiſs, but I have alſo done that which is evil in thy ſight, thou knoweſt in how many places, how often, and with what Circumſtances; for thou telleſt all my ſteps, and obſerveſt all my wandrings, <hi>When I ſin thou markest me, for thou knoweſt my down-ſitting and mine upriſing, thou compaſſeſt my
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:105036:30"/>path, (Job.</hi> 10.14.) <hi>and art ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with all my ways. (Pſal.</hi> 139.2, 3.) Thou knoweſt how little I have minded what thou haſt given me in charge; how induſtrious and diligent I have been in my worldly affairs, how remiſs and cold about my ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual concernments, how wiſe to lay up a treaſure for my ſelf on earth, and how careleſs in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding for my precious and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Soul. Thou knoweſt how little delight I have had in thy Word and worſhip, how lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle zeal there hath been in me for thine Honour and Glory; how I have ſatisfied my ſelf oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in holy duties with the work done, not ſufficiently caring whether my communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with thee were improved by my approaching to thee. And when I have been about thoſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:105036:30"/>ſecular employments, which thou allowedſt me to be buſied in under the Sun, how little have I ſerved thee in them! Or hearkned to the directions thou haſt given in thy word for men to follow in their worldly la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours! So that if my eſtate and wealth, and honour, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Accommodations ſhould <hi>prove ſnares</hi> unto my ſoul (as <hi>they</hi> do to thouſands, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 69.22.) and occaſions of my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrying unto all eternity, I muſt acknowledg thy juſtice, and blame none but my ſelf, who have refuſed to hearken to thy counſail, and would not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded there was any danger to be feared in ſuch things. And yet how often have I heard, and read in thy Word, that, <hi>the cares of this World and the deceitfulneſs of Riches do choak
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:105036:31"/>the World, ſo that it becomes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitful, (Mat.</hi> 13.22.) And thereupon, that <hi>thoſe that are rich ſhall very hardly enter</hi> into <hi>the Kingdom of Heaven (Mat.</hi> 19.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.24.) How apt have I been <hi>to truſt in uncertain riches, rather than in the living God,</hi> (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.17) to make Silver and Gold my confidence, and to have my heart ſtollen away from thee? And for thoſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents thou haſt truſted me with, how ready have I been to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get that I am but a ſteward, that nothing I have (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.8, 9. <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.10) <hi>is mine own,</hi> but <hi>that all is thine,</hi> and to be diſpoſed of as thou preſcribeſt. For, Lord! What have I, that I have not receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and muſt not be accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for? Much thou haſt done for me, more than for thouſands,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:105036:31"/>and ten thouſands; but where hath been my thankfulneſs, mine obedience, my care to pleaſe thee ſo much the more for all the good thou haſt ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me and done for me! Thou haſt reached out to me with a liberal hand. <hi>My beginning was but ſmall (Job.</hi> 8.7.) and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, <hi>but thou hast greatly increaſed my latter end.</hi> What outward Bleſſing, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of eſtate, or of repute, or of health, or of long life, or of a numerous and hopeful poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, do I want? What a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of dangers, and <hi>hazards, (Pſal.</hi> 107.23, 24, 25, 26.) and troubles by Sea and Land, by Night and Day haſt thou mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully carryed me through? But ah! my unthankfulneſs, my forgetfulneſs of that God, who hath thus watched over me, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:105036:32"/>preſerved me, and provided for me and mine, hitherto! And upon whoſe bounty and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs I have lived all my days! Ah what poor returns have I made for all that I have receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Are there not many of thy Saints, who, in want, and ſcarci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of what I enjoy, have done thee more faithful ſervice, lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee better, been more zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for thy Glory, yea more thankful, than I, in the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all that I have enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Ah Lord! no words are ſufficient to ſet out my ſins and the hainouſneſs of them, which have been committed; ſome of them againſt Conſcience, and knowledg of my duty; ſome of them oft fallen into, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in long; ſome of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt many renewed purpoſes and vows of better obedience:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:105036:32"/>all of them againſt many calls and invitations from thee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, and againſt many ſignal favours of thine vouchſaf'd to me unworthy. Bleſſed Father! Thou knoweſt my ſins better than I do, and they are all of them ſo many debts, which are recorded in thy book. Lord, I have nothing at all to pay of thoſe infinite ſummes which I owe unto thy dreadful juſtice; I have no way to make thee any amends or ſatisfaction. Lord, I do <hi>here judg my ſelf</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31.) worthy of what ever pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhment, either in this life, or that which is to come, thy Word hath denounced againſt ſinners. I deſerve to lye everlaſtingly under thy curſe. If thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſend me unto Hell, I muſt, <hi>I will juſtifie thee (Pſal.</hi> 51.4.) in thy proceedings, and ſay, It is
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:105036:33"/>I only that have undone my ſelf.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The next thing to be done in order to the ſuing out our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, is, to plead the Satisfaction and payment which Chriſt hath made to Divine juſtice for the ſins of ſo many as lay hold on him, and penitently ſeek pardon and favour from God through his blood. For, <hi>He (Joh.</hi> 1.29.) <hi>is that Lamb of God which taketh away the ſins of the world, and his blood ſpeaketh better things than the blood of Abel doth (Heb.</hi> 12.24.) This is to take ſanctuary at the horns of that Altar, from which a believing and repenting ſinner ſhall not be pulled away. This is like the eſcaping to the City of refuge from the Avenger of blood: In a word, it is to fly from God, by flying to him; to fly from his juſtice by flying to
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:105036:33"/>his mercy. <q>Lord! I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved thy wrath, and it might be juſt with thee <hi>to write bitter things againſt me, (Job.</hi> 13.26.) for the ſins of my youth, and of my riper years. My ſins are ſo many, my guilt ſo black and horrid, that the Devil tempts me to deſpair, and my own heart is ready to miſgive me, and to tell me, there is no mercy for me, that I come now too late, and ſhall not be accepted. And if the mercy and grace that hath been ſo oft offered to me and ſlighted by me, ſhould now be denyed me: if now that I come to knock, thou ſhouldeſt bid me depart, and refuſe to take any notice of me, I muſt confeſs thou ſhouldeſt be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous. Thou haſt called <hi>on me and I have refuſed, thou haſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a time ſtretched out thy hand
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:105036:34"/>to me and I regarded thee not; how juſtly therefore might I call and not be heard, and ſeek thee with importunity and not find thee! (Prov.</hi> 1.24, 25, 28.) Lord, my Conſcience accuſeth me, my own heart condemns me and is ready to paſs ſentence againſt me. But, bleſſed Father! Is not thy grace free, and doeſt thou not uſe to beſtow it upon ſuch as are both undeſerving and ill deſerving too? Doth not the mercy and compaſſion of God as far exceed the mercy and compaſſion of the moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-hearted among the Sons and Daughters of men, <hi>as the Heaven is higher than the Earth? (Iſa.</hi> 55.9.) Haſt thou not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that this is thy Name, (<hi>Exod.</hi> 34.6, 7.) <hi>The Lord, The Lord God merciful and gracious, long ſuffering, and abundant in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:105036:34"/>goodneſs and truth, keeping mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for thouſands, forgiving ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, tranſgreſſion and ſin;</hi> that is, ſins of all ſorts, ſins that one hath been habituated in, and accuſtomed unto? Yea and that I might have ſtrong <hi>conſolation through hope, (Heb.</hi> 6.17, 18.) thou <hi>haſt ſworn</hi> that thou (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11.) <hi>delighteſt not in the death of a ſinner, but rather that he ſhould repent.</hi> And haſt told me that <hi>thou blotteſt out the tranſgreſſions (Iſa.</hi> 43.25.) of ſinners <hi>freely for thy own ſake.</hi> If none ſhould be received to mercy but thoſe that deſerved it, and were worthy of it; there would be cauſe indeed for me to wring my hands, and lye down in horrour and deſpair: But as long as thy grace is free, my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs can be no hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to me from obtaining thy
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:105036:35"/>favour, which thou art wont to ſhew only to unworthy ones for thy names ſake. And though, Holy and Glorious Lord! I am not able to make the leaſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, or to pay one farthing of that dreadful ſumm, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſtand indebted to thy Juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice; yet, I am ſure, there hath been a full and complete Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction made to that infinite Juſtice of thine, and that by thine own and ever bleſſed Son, in behalf of as many poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, as, feeling their extreme need of ſuch a Saviour, plead his righteouſneſs, and beg mercy upon his Account. He was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered unto death, the cruel and curſed death of the Croſs <hi>for our offences, (Rom.</hi> 4.25.) <hi>and was raiſed again for our juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</hi> He <hi>was bruiſed for our iniquities, and the chaſtiſement
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:105036:35"/>of our peace was upon him, and by his stripes (Iſa.</hi> 53.5.) poor ſinners are healed. And I read further in thy word of trueth, that the Lord Jeſus (<hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25.) <hi>is able to the uttermoſt to ſave all ſuch</hi> (Ah! What a ſweet and comfortable word is that!) <hi>All ſuch as come to God through him.</hi> This is all I have to alledg and ſay for my ſelf, and this is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, Lord: I deſire no more, to plead before the Tribunal of thy juſtice but only the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of thy Son. I hope he hath accounted for my ſins, my original ſin, my actual rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, all thoſe evils that I have been guilty of, and lived ſo long in, and that therefore they ſhall not be charged upon me. The blood of Chriſt, I know, is ſufficient to cleanſe from all ſins, even <hi>thoſe which are as
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:105036:36"/>Searlet, and as Crimſon (Iſa.</hi> 1.18.) Nor is it any preſumption for me, or any poor ſinner (upon thine encouragement) to hope for an intereſt and part in that redemption which that Bleſſed Son of thine hath wrought, for I have learned in thy word, that the ſalvation procured by him is a <hi>common ſalvation (Jude v.</hi> 3.) not limited and reſtrayned to a few only, but purchaſed for, and offered to <hi>all that will;</hi> and whoſoever will is bidden <hi>to come, and take of the water of life freely (Rev.</hi> 22.17.) and <hi>whoſoever is a thirſt to buy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out money and without price (Iſa.</hi> 55.1.) And though I am an hainous ſinner (as I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs;) yet Lord! Have not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grievous and horrid ſinners been received unto mercy? The Apoſtle ſpeaking of himſelf and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:105036:36"/>other believers that had found mercy, ſaith, (<hi>Tit.</hi> 3.3.) <hi>We our ſelves were ſometime fooliſh, diſobedient, ſerving divers luſts and pleaſures living in malice and envy, hateful and hating one another.</hi> And the ſame Holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle tells the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that ſome of them who had formerly been <hi>fornicatours, adulterers, theeves, drunkards, covetous, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioners, and guilty of other foul and horrid ſins,</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.9, 10, 11.) were yet, through grace, <hi>waſhed, and juſtified,</hi> and pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſanctified. What an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite number of poor ſinners, have been healed and cleanſed by the Blood of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; And indeed, What caſe can be deſperate, when ſuch a Phyſician is pleaſed to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Cure? And though I come thus late, and even almoſt
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:105036:37"/>at the eleventh hour, yet why ſhould I deſpair as long as I hear my dear Lord and Saviour cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling me, and ſaying unto me, Come: <hi>Come thou that are weary and heavy laden, (Mat.</hi> 11.28.) Return thou backſliding ſoul, and I will heal thee. I come, Lord, as well as my feeble ſtrength will permit; <hi>Draw me and I will run faſter, (Cant.</hi> 1.4.) I would fain believe (<hi>Mar.</hi> 9.24.) <hi>help me againſt my unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</hi> Make me partaker of thy pardoning grace. Oh! <hi>Happy are they whoſe iniquities are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given, and whoſe ſins are covered! (Pſal.</hi> 32.1, 2.) <hi>Bleſſed are they to whom God imputes not their ſin.</hi> Bleſſed are they between whom and thy wrath, Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſeth himſelf as a skreen, to keep them from the heat of thy fiery indignation. And Oh! Let
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:105036:37"/>me be ſo happy as to have a part in this priviledg; then will I fing, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.6.) <hi>The lines are faln to me in a pleaſant place, and I have a goodly heritage for God is my portion.</hi> What is long life, and honour, and a great Eſtate, or any thing, or all things that this world affords, if my ſins ſhould be charged upon me; and I be ſent to priſon, till I had paid every farthing of the debt I owe to thy juſtice? What good will all theſe things do me, if I be not juſtified, and pardoned, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into thy favour through Chriſt? Oh, for Chriſt's ſake let me <hi>be remembred with the mercy, (with this mercy) thou ſhewest to thy choſen ones; Oh! Viſit me with thy ſalvation (Pſal.</hi> 106.4.) Save me from my ſins, and by thy grace I will be thy ſervant, and own thee for my Lord; my Soul,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:105036:38"/>and Body and Eſtate, and all I have ſhall be at thy command. Oh! Save me, and I ſhall glorifie thee, and ſing Hallelu-jah to thee with all thy Redeemed ones, to all Eternity.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Third and laſt thing to be done in order to a preparation for our comfortable departure hence, is, daily to <hi>give all diligence to make our election</hi> ſure, (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.) that is, to labour to get ſome evidence, (which will not deceive us) that we are of the number of thoſe for whom that <hi>inheritance in Heaven, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptible, undefiled, and never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fadeth away, is reſerved</hi> (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.) How this may be done the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle tells us, <hi>viz.</hi> by <hi>making our effectual calling ſure</hi> (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.) So that if we can get ſome infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble evidence of our Vocation, we may ſafely from thence conclude
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:105036:38"/>our Election from all eternity, &amp; ſo our Salvation in the world to come! And how cheerfully may <hi>he lay down</hi> this <hi>earthly tabernacle,</hi> that knows, <hi>when it is diſſolved, he hath a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.)</p>
            <p>What the ſigns of effectual Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling are, will eaſily be diſcerned, if we do but conſider what effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Calling is, and wherein it doth conſiſt. And it is nothing but this: <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Bleſſed work of Gods Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power and free grace, whereby poor miſerable ſinners, whom he hath a favour for, and who, by nature lye dead in treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes and ſins among the reſt of mankind, are made, in his due time, to hear the voyce of His Word and Spirit; ſo that their eyes are opened, their hearts are
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:105036:39"/>changed and renewed, and they ſo hearken to his Call, that they are (<hi>Joh.</hi> 6.44.) <hi>drawn</hi> off from their ſins and vanities, unto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with himſelf by Faith in his Son, and give up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves wholly to be at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>Effectual Vocation therefore makes a manifeſt and a mervail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous change in a man, from what he was before: He ſees theſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and eternal things, within the vail which were formerly hidden from his eyes, his heart love's and cloſes with thoſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, which formerly, as he had no fight of, ſo he had no affections for: And there is, in a manner, as much difference between the man and himſelf, as there was betwixt <hi>Lazarus</hi> lying in the grave, and <hi>Lazarus</hi> riſing and coming forth at the call of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:105036:39"/>
            <p>A man may therefore certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know his Effectual Vocation by five ſings. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The frame and temper of his heart toward ſin, from which he is called off.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The workings of his Soul toward God, who doth ſo graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly call him to Himſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The value and price he puts upon Chriſt, through whom he hopes for acceptance.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The eſteem he hath of Gods Ordinances, the means whereby his effectual Vocation hath been wrought.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The reſpect he bears to Gods precepts, which are the Rule of Life to all that are called.</p>
            <p>He that deals impartially in the examination of himſelf upon theſe particulars cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p>The firſt ſign, is the frame of our
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:105036:40"/>hearts toward ſin, which, if we be effectually called, will be this:</p>
            <p>God in this bleſſed work of Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, calls us off from ſin unto communion with Himſelf. And therefore the perſon that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led effectually, looks upon all ſin with deteſtation, as knowing, nothing ſeparates between God and him, but that only: he is much in ſearching, and examination of himſelf, and that impartially, that he may find out whatever he hath done amiſs, ſo far as he can; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares, (for that end,) his life with Gods moſt perfect Law, yea and begs of God earneſtly, with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, (Pſal.</hi> 139.23) to <hi>ſearch him, and diſcover to him, if there be any way of wickedneſs in him.</hi> He hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles himſelf deeply before God for all the evil he finds in his heart and life. He repents unfain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, and ſhews his repentance by
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:105036:40"/>a godly ſorrow, mourning chiefly becauſe he hath offended God. He labours to make what amends he can, by doing God ſo much the more ſervice in his place, for the future, and by making <hi>Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Reſtitution</hi> where his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience tells him he hath wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or injured any perſon (<hi>Luk.</hi> 19.8.) He firmly reſolves by Gods grace to look better to his ſteps, the reſidue of his days; and to fight and watch againſt all ſin, his ſpecial ſins eſpecially, as being the Bane of his Soul, and working all his woe. To that purpoſe (in ſenſe of his own weakneſs) he ſends up ardent and frequent cries to Heaven, for help and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and with all importunity begs pardon through the blood of Chriſt. He is grieved to ſee God offended by others, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by thoſe whom he loves; and<pb n="80" facs="tcp:105036:41"/>improves his authority and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, where he hath any, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, than the ſuppreſſing of ſin, ſpecially in his family, and in them over whom God hath given him any charge. In a word, the perſon effectually called is troubled for nothing more then ſin, hates nothing more; there is nothing he would ſo fain be rid of, as that body of ſin, and death, he carries about with him; cryes out with the Apoſtle, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.) <hi>Wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliver me?</hi> Sin is that which he beareth and groneth under as his greateſt burden, which he prayes againſt, watcheth and ſtrives againſt to his very laſt, and would count it as his greateſt happineſs to be freed from.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the workings of his ſoul toward God; they are theſe, and ſuch like in one that is effectually called. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:105036:41"/>
            <p>Though once he had but low thoughts of God and of his love, and prized the favour of men more; and, ſo he might keep in with men, God was hardly, to any purpoſe, in his thoughts: yet now through grace, it is otherwiſe with him. He ſets an infinite price and value upon Gods favour, and fully aſſents unto the Pſalmiſt (<hi>Pſ.</hi> 4.6.) <hi>Many ſay who will ſhew</hi> us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>good, but Lord lift thou up the light of thy countenance upon me, and that ſhall cauſe a gladneſs in my ſoul greater than any the men of this World have, when their Corn and Oyl, and all their earthly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments do moſt increaſe.</hi> And as he deſires and pants after nothing more then Gods love, ſo he bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to God a love <hi>as strong as death: (Cant.</hi> 8.6.) Lov's <hi>him with all his heart and ſtrength and might, (Matt.</hi> 22.37.) Lov's him
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:105036:42"/>more then wife, children, relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, more then his eſtate and wealth. He ſaith with the Pſalm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſt (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25.) <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee, and what is there upon Earth that I deſire beſide thee?</hi> He pants after <hi>Communion with God, as the Hart brayes</hi> after <hi>the water-brooks, (Pſal.</hi> 42.1.) And this love he bears to God ſhews it ſelf in his ſincere Affection and love to all Gods people, and his readineſs to do all offices of love to them, as he is able, (1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.1.) <hi>He that loveth him that begot, lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him alſo that is begotten of him.</hi> And <hi>hereby do we know that we are tranſlated from death to life, if we love the brethren</hi> (1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.14.)</p>
            <p n="3">3. A man may know himſelf to be effectually called and ſo elect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the eſteem he hath of Jeſus Chriſt; for he puts a value upon him no leſs then infinite. And the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:105036:42"/>reaſon is plain: ſuch perſons, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever once they accounted not much of Chriſt (like unto others that are unregenerate,) and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited they could have made a ſhift without him, yet now they ſee an excellency in him, that makes him in their eyes the <hi>chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est of ten thouſand, (Cant.</hi> 5.10.) and inwardly feel a need of him greater than can be expreſſed and uttered. Now with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, (<hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.) <hi>they count all things but droſs and dogs-meat in compariſon of Chriſt. Their ſouls are even ſick of love unto him. (Cant.</hi> 5.8.) All their hope and Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence is placed in him, all their Expectations are from him: They utterly renounce all their own righteouſneſs, and hope for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with the Father meerly and alone upon his account. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an intereſt in his righteouſneſs
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:105036:43"/>they hunger and thirſt. They place all their happineſs <hi>in having him</hi> to be theirs, and in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his, (<hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16.) <hi>My beloved is mine, and I am his,</hi> ſaith the Church, and that was all ſhe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for. In a word Chriſt is to the perſon effectually called, <hi>All in All (Col.</hi> 3.11.) He is <hi>All</hi> to him in the enjoyment of <hi>All; All</hi> that he hath is unpleaſant to him, and wants its taſte and reliſh, if he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy not Chriſt; He is <hi>All</hi> to him in the want of <hi>All:</hi> If he have Chriſt he wants nothing: He can find in Him All that his ſoul deſires. So great is his affection to Him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. A man may gather a certain evidence of his effectual Calling by the account alſo he makes of Gods ordinances. For ſuch a one values his liberty to enjoy them above his outward Accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. <hi>Oh How amiable are thy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:105036:43"/>O Lord of Hoſts! I had rather be a door keeper there, then to dwell in the tents of wickedneſs, (Pſal.</hi> 84.1.) He finds an unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able need that his ſoul hath of them. <hi>Job</hi> could no more live (<hi>Job</hi> 23.12.) <hi>without the word of God, then his body could ſubſiſt without his daily food.</hi> He grievs for want of them, more then for want of his chiefeſt accommodations: Hence is that Promiſe, which ſhews what is in the heart of a gracious perſon: (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.20.) <hi>Though the Lord give you the bread of adverſity, and the water of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, yet ſhall not thy teachers be removed into a corner any more, but thine eyes ſhall ſee thy teachers.</hi> Implying, that (to a gracious ſoul) the enjoying of God in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances will make amends for the want of temporal mercies and comforts. And we read, that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:105036:44"/>when <hi>David</hi> was baniſhed from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by reaſon of <hi>Abſolons</hi> riſing up in rebellion againſt him, this was the thing which chiefly troubled him, and went unto his heart, that he could <hi>not ſee (Pſal.</hi> 42.1, 2, 3, 4.) God, and enjoy him in his Sanctuary, as he was wont to do.</p>
            <p n="5">5. A fifth trial of a mans effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual Calling, is the reſpect he hath to Gods commandments. For ſuch a one will deſire to know and be acquainted with all Gods Will, ſpecially that part which concern's his own duty moſt: His Query will be (<hi>Act.</hi> 9.6.) <hi>Lord what wouldſt thou have me do?</hi> He will not allow himſelf in the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of any thing which God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, nor pick and chuſe among Gods precepts, thoſe which are moſt eaſie, and leaſt dangerous, and ſuit beſt with his own diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:105036:44"/>or intereſt, and ſhow his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience only there: Indeed, that is no obedience at all; for there is no man ſo bad but doth ſome thing which God requires, and abſtains from ſome ſins which God forbid's. He is no good Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant that will do but what he liſt, of that which his Maſter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. And though no perfection is attainable in this life, yet the ſincere Chriſtian pants and breathes after perfection; prays daily for more grace, to ſerve God better, ſets himſelf no ſtint, is humbled deeply for his daily failings, begs for pardon, and runs to Chriſt for ſtrength to do better, without <hi>whom he knows he can do nothing, (Joh.</hi> 15.5.) And thus, by <hi>ſhewing his ſincere reſpect to all Gods Commandments (Pſal.</hi> 119.6.) of firſt and ſecond Table both (though he can perform
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:105036:45"/>none of them as he deſires) he gets ſome comfortable evidence to his own ſoul, that he <hi>ſhall never periſh and be confounded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that can by theſe ſigns prove his effectual calling, may ſafely from thence conclude his electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for ſo the Apoſtle teacheth us (2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.) where he bids us but make our calling ſure, and we have all under one made our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection ſure too. And he that can do thus, may be confident upon good ground, that death, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it come ſooner, or later can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hurt him; yea that death ſhall be ſo far from doing him any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, that it ſhall be for his greateſt advantage.</p>
            <p>If any ſhould think the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſigns ſerve only for thoſe of Chriſts Diſciples that be of the higheſt form: They are miſtaken; for, where there is but ſo much
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:105036:45"/>grace <hi>as a grain of muſtardſeed,</hi> it will diſcover it ſelf by loving God above all, by putting ſuch a value upon Chriſt, as upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more, by being grieved at the very heart for ſin, and hating it with a perfect deteſtation, by prizing highly thoſe Ordinances whereby God admits us (here) unto communion with himſelf; by loving all Gods people deerly, and ſhewing reſpect to all his precepts, without allowing and indulging our ſelves in any ſin. He that loves God and Chriſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther leſs than, or but as much as, ſome other thing, cannot truely be ſaid to love him at all. As he that loves his Wife, or his Child, but as he loves an Horſe, or a Dog, hath certainly neither the affection of an Husband, nor of a Father in him. The leaſt meaſure of the true love of God is to love
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:105036:46"/>him above all; the leaſt meaſure of true ſorrow for ſin is to grieve for it more then any thing elſe: The loweſt degree of true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, is, to have reſpect unto all Gods precepts.</p>
            <p>When we have laboured thus to make our calling and election ſure (for both are done with one and the ſame labour) there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains nothing further incumbent upon us in order to our comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſurrendring our ſouls into the hands of God, at the time of our death, but to be daily exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thoſe two main graces of Faith and Repentance, till the hour of our appointed change do come. The exerciſe of them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in theſe four Particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In ſearching our hearts and lives daily, to find out what hath been amiſs in either; for which purpoſe, we are to view our ſelvs
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:105036:46"/>often in the glaſs of Gods pure and perfect law.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In labouring to be more and more deeply humbled for our miſcarriages, and to work our hearts yet to a greater meaſure of godly ſorrow for them, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In ſtirring up our ſelves to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, and labouring to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en our faith, by the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the freeneſs of Gods grace, and the infinite value of Chriſts Satisfaction, which is ſufficient to make an Atonement for the greateſt Sinners. To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we muſt be meditating ever and anon upon the Covenant of Grace, wherein nothing at all is required to make us partakers of Chriſt and his Benefits, but that (<hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12.) <hi>we accept</hi> and be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: Chriſt ſhall for certain be ours, and, with him, we ſhall have
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:105036:47"/>Heaven and eternal happineſs, if we be willing heartily to accept him as he is offered in the Goſpel, that is, (<hi>Act.</hi> 5.31.) to be <hi>our King and Prophet,</hi> as well <hi>as our</hi> Prieſt and Saviour. <hi>He that will, let him take of the Water of Life freely.</hi> (<hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17.) We muſt conſider <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow many wretched and forlorn ſinners, ſome of which have come in at the <hi>eleventh hour,</hi> have been received to mercy; and that it is Gods way to ſhew mercy only to unworthy ones, (<hi>Rom.</hi> 5.20.) that his grace may be the more mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified. We muſt remember and ponder oft, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the Wold on purpoſe to <hi>ſeek and ſave thoſe that are loſt,</hi> (<hi>Luk.</hi> 19.10.) and that he hath promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, None <hi>that come to him ſhall be rejected or</hi> caſt off. (<hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37.)</p>
            <p n="4">4. Laſtly in frequent and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Prayer, for pardon of ſin, for
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:105036:47"/>the graces we find wanting, for the ſtrengthning of our Faith, and reſolution of all holy obedience, for help againſt the tentations of Satan (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12.) <hi>Lord, who can underſtand his errours, cleanſe thou me</hi> from my ſecret faults. Pardon to me all the ſins I know by my ſelf, and all thoſe ſins which thou haſt taken notice of, that I have not obſerved. Work me to a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſaving Humiliation, ſtrengthen my weak Faith, (<hi>Mar.</hi> 9.24.) <hi>help my unbeleif,</hi> Lord! Is not the blood of Chriſt, if it were applyed to my ſoul, ſufficient to fetch out the ſtains of all my ſins? I know it is. Is not thy Mercy free? And haſt not thou bidden <hi>me, Come without money,</hi> (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1.) and incouraged all that will come, to hope for mercy? Lord, I would fain repent better, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve better, and love thee better,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:105036:48"/>and obey better: But what can I do without thy grace? Oh! Let thy ſpirit help my infirmity. I do deſire to lay hold on the Scepter of thy Mercy. Oh! Deny not thy mercy to me. Kill my ſins that my ſoul may live. Tread Satan under my feet, help me againſt his fiery darts. Let me not be overcome with his tentations to diffidence, and diſtruſt. Help me to believe, and repent, and pray, and wait, and to continue knocking at the door of grace till my laſt gaſp.</p>
            <p>In ſuch exerciſes, and medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as theſe, ſome part of every day ſhould be ſpent. And though it ſhould ſo fall out, that we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain not to that meaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Aſſurance, which we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; yet we need not be diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, but are to hold on praying and knocking, and waiting, and to throw our ſelves into the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:105036:48"/>Arms of Jeſus Chriſt, bleeding inwardly for all our unkindneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to him, beſeeching and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of him that he would paſs them by.</p>
            <p>He that lives and dyes pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and repenting, and believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and crying for mercy through Chriſt, and doth ſo ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely (though haply he obtain not that comfort which God vouchſafeth to ſome others) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not miſcarry.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="recommended_Bible_reading">
            <pb facs="tcp:105036:49"/>
            <head>Places of Scripture to be often read, and meditated on.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE 22.31, 32. chapters of <hi>Job.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 38.39, 42, 49, 51, 62, 71, 73, 88, 89, 90, 94, 103, 116, 119, 139, 143, 135. <hi>Pſalms.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 3. chap. of <hi>Prov.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 12 chap. of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 38, 53, 55, 58. of <hi>Iſa.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 5.6, 7, 13, 18, 19, 25, 26, 27. of <hi>Matt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 12.13, 14, 15, 16, 19. of <hi>Luke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 7.8. of the Epiſt. to the <hi>Rom.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 15. of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 14.15, 16, 17. of <hi>John.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 5. of 2 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 4.5. of 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 6. of 1 <hi>Tim.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 2. of <hi>Tit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 11.12. of <hi>Heb.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 2.3. of <hi>James.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The firſt Epiſtle of <hi>John.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The 2.3, 21, 22. of <hi>Revel.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:105036:49"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
